<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Epistola Medio-Saxonica, or, Middlesex first letter to His Excellency, the Lord General Cromwell together with their petition concerning tithes and copy-holds of inheritance, presented to the supreme authority, the Parliament of England : wherein the tortious and illegal usurpation of tithes, contrary to Magna Charta, is discovered, the blemished dignity of copy-holders revived, and how lords of manors have formerly incroached upon their liberties, by imposing arbitrary fines, and multiplying of heriots : whereunto is annexed two additional cases concerning the unreasonable exactions of fines and heriots, contrary to law, in these latter times ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38520</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3170</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5296</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12138585</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12138585</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54824</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38520)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54824)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 28:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Epistola Medio-Saxonica, or, Middlesex first letter to His Excellency, the Lord General Cromwell together with their petition concerning tithes and copy-holds of inheritance, presented to the supreme authority, the Parliament of England : wherein the tortious and illegal usurpation of tithes, contrary to Magna Charta, is discovered, the blemished dignity of copy-holders revived, and how lords of manors have formerly incroached upon their liberties, by imposing arbitrary fines, and multiplying of heriots : whereunto is annexed two additional cases concerning the unreasonable exactions of fines and heriots, contrary to law, in these latter times ...</title>
                  <author>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658.</author>
                  <author>Wingfield, Augustus. Vindiciae Medico-Saxonicae.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>20, [2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by F.L. for William Larnar ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Vindiciae Medico-Saxonicae, or Tithes totally routed, by Magna Charta" by Aug. Wingfield has separate t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Magna Carta.</term>
               <term>Taxation --  England.</term>
               <term>Copyhold.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:54824:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:54824:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Epiſtola Medio-Saxonica,</hi> OR, <hi>Middleſex</hi> firſt Letter to his Excellency, The Lord General Cromwell: Together with their Petition concerning Tithes and Copy-holds of Inheritance, preſented to the Supreme Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, <hi>The Parliament of ENGLAND.</hi> Wherein the tortious and illegal Uſurpation of Tithes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> is diſcovered, the blemiſhed dignity of Copy-hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders revived, and how Lords of Manors have formerly incroached upon their liberties, by impoſing Arbitrary Fines, and multiplying of Heriots. Whereunto is annexed two Additional Caſes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the unreaſonable exactions of Fines and Heriots, contrary to Law, in theſe latter times. Publiſhed for the ſatisfaction and vindication of the people of <hi>England,</hi> from all Decimal Oppreſſion and Lordly Tyranny. The Second Edition; To which is added a Reply, Styl'd, <hi>Tithes totally routed by</hi> Magna Charta.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>F. L.</hi> for <hi>William Larnar,</hi> at the <hi>Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more,</hi> near <hi>Fleet-Bridge,</hi> 1653.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:54824:2"/>
                  <head>In Decimas &amp; ſerva Praedia, Carmen Hexaſtichon.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>SI mos Angliacus, nec ſacra oracula ſuadent,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cur ſolvis Decimas, Anglia luſa, tuas?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Si felix rediit ſeclum, victique Tyranni,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cur ſervile feres, Anglia maeſta, jugum?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sic pia vota tulit Miles, totuſque Senatus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Reddere cur differs, Anglia, vota Deo?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Vpon Tithes and Copy-holds, an Hexaſtick Verſe.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>IF Engliſh Cuſtome, nor Gods Words perſwade,</l>
                     <l>Why yet are Tithes, deceived England, paid?</l>
                     <l>If th'age of Gold be come, and Tyrants broke,</l>
                     <l>Why doſt thou, England, bear the ſervile Yoke?</l>
                     <l>If th' Army, and the Senate, Vows have made,</l>
                     <l>Why are they by them, England, thus delay'd?</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:54824:2"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Middleſex</hi> firſt Letter to his Excellency.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>May it pleaſe your Excellency.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſweet odour of your name, and unparallel'd af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection towards goodneſſe, and good people, hath imboldned us, in the behalf, and at the intreaty of the wel-affected of this County, to communicate to your Excellency, our intended <hi>Addreſſes</hi> by way of Petition to the <hi>Supreme Authority,</hi> for the removal of ſome grievances which have layen long and heavy upon the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born people of this Nation; that ſo receiving your judicious appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation and aſſiſtance, we might with the greater alacrity make our procedure. Now Sir, the Heads of our Petition are onely two; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the removal of that uſurped Popiſh relique Tithes, and the aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of that Tyrannical Oppreſſion and ſlaviſh tenure of Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds of inheritance, finably at the Lords will, as things Diametrical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repugnant to divine and humane Laws, <hi>Lev.</hi> 25.14. <hi>Ye ſhall not oppreſs one another,</hi> and <hi>Ier.</hi> 30.20. <hi>I will puniſh all that oppreſs the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> where your Excellency may be pleaſed to take notice of a prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not to oppreſs the people of God, and of a puniſhment threatned to thoſe that do it. And in <hi>Exo.</hi> 23.5. There is a command, that if we ſee the Aſs of our enemy lying under a burthen, that we ſhall not paſſe by but help him: If therefore an oppreſſed brute Creature ought to be relieved by us, how much more a rational? how much more a Chriſtian and wel-affected people? who in the blackeſt times of danger and peril, have adhered to the State with undanted reſolutions, adventuring lives, goods, and all, for the glory of God, and the preſervation of this Common-wealth; wherefore let not, O let not our State bury in ſilence the day of this peoples love, who, next to your Excellency and renowned Army, under God, have been a principal means of the glorious freedom our State now enjoyes. But becauſe moſt men look more upon humane, than divine Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, eſpecially where their own private intereſt falls in; and as it is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54824:3"/>in the 5th. Book of <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Ethicks, Can be vertuous and juſt in matters of their own concernment, but not ſo in what concerns the publique, which occaſioned <hi>Nobile illud dictum Biantis,</hi> that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſaying of that Grecian Sage, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Power will diſcover the nature and diſpoſition of every man. Therefore for the ſatisfaction of thoſe, whoſe judgements are over-ballanced in the ſcale of earthly intereſt, (not in the leaſt reflecting on your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, whom we experimentally know to be of a more divine temper) we ſhall in brief produce ſome humane authorities, as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to the removall of the aforeſaid grievances:</p>
                  <p>Firſt by the 29th. Chapter of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> It is enacted, That no man ſhall be diſſeiſſed, or put out of his free Tenement, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or Cuſtomes, but by the lawfull judgements of his Peers, or Law of the Land: which Charter is of ſo great authority, that it hath been confirmed above thirty times. Now Tithes being a part of every mans free-Tenement, or free-hold and birth right, ought not to be taken away from him, either by the Impropriate Perſon, or Appropriate Parſon, for theſe reaſons.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Becauſe by the Stat. of 25. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>ch.</hi> 2. All judgements given againſt any points of the Charters of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> or <hi>Chartade Foreſta,</hi> are adjudged void.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, by the Stat. of 42 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>ch.</hi> 1. If any Statute be hereafter made againſt either of theſe Statutes, it ſhall be void. <hi>Cookes</hi> 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Juſt. fo.</hi> 81.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, in <hi>Bonhams</hi> Caſe, in the 8th. Book of <hi>Cooks</hi> Reports, and in <hi>Dr.</hi> and <hi>Student,</hi> it is laid down for Law, that Acts of Parliament againſt common Right or Reaſon, are <hi>ipſo facto</hi> void.</p>
                  <p>And laſtly, it is proved by <hi>Jenkins, fol.</hi> 139. That the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law ſhall controle Acts of Parliament made againſt Right or Reaſon, (ſuch as all Statutes for Tithes are) and adjudge them to be void, becauſe they deprive men of a part of their right, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and againſt the will of the Proprietor or owner; ſo that hence it will plainly appear, that thoſe Statutes which have been made by former Parliaments concerning Tithes, in times of Popery and ignorance, and upon falſe grounds of their Divine Right, being Diametrically repugnant to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and deſtructive of common right, then were, and now are, totally void, null, and of no force; and that all Tithes taken by virtue of them, have been uſurped, illegal, and unwarrantable. And
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54824:3"/>becauſe ſome ſeeing the weakneſſe of their Statute-Law foundation, may fly from thence to the Umbrage and ſhelter of cuſtome; we anſwer. It is a Maxim in Law, that a man cannot claim any thing by Cuſtome or Preſcription, againſt a Statute, unleſſe the Cuſtome or Preſcription be ſaved by another Statute, <hi>Cooks</hi> 2. <hi>p. Juſt. fo.</hi> 21. Now by the aforeſaid Charter of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> which was confirmed by <hi>H.</hi> 3. about the year, 1218. Tithes as well as the reſt did belong to every mans Tenement and Free-hold, and ſo far were the Clergy at that time from claiming any Tithes to be due un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them by any Cuſtome, as that, on the contrary, it is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged at the Councill of <hi>Lateran,</hi> under <hi>Gregory</hi> the 10th. <hi>Anno</hi> 1274. and in the Decretal Epiſtle ſent from Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the 3d. to the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> about the year 1215. that the people of this Nation did by a general Cuſtome till then obſerved, diſpoſe of their Tithes according to their own free will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. So that it is very clear at the confirmation of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> no Cuſtome of the Land for Clergy-men to have Tithes out of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Proprietors Eſtate, but that they were the proper right and inheritance of the owner of the Land. And for confirmation here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, it is ſaid by learned <hi>Selden</hi> in his book of Tithes, that in <hi>H.</hi> 2. his time, which was a little before the ſaid Decretal, Parochi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al right was the right of having the Cure and offering of the Pariſhiones; and that to that Parochial right, no right of Tithes was annexed by the practiſe of that time. Whereupon it was uſual with the Religious and ſecular of the Clergy, to covenant with their Tenants to pay them the Tithes of their Lands, that ſo they might prevent the Miniſter of the Pariſh, where the Lands lay. Now if there had been then any Parochial right or cuſtom for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving Tithes, how could ſuch a Covenant have prevented the Parochial Miniſter? And that this is a clear truth, is evidenced by an Act of Parliament, in the firſt year of <hi>Rich.</hi> the 2. and in the year of our Lord 1377. in theſe words, It is accorded, that at what time any perſon of Holy Church be drawn in plea in the Secular Court for his Tithes taken by the name of Goods taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; and he, which is ſo drawn in plea, maketh an exception, or allegeth, that the ſubſtance and ſute of the buſineſſe is only upon Tithes, due of right and of Poſſeſſion to his Church, or to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Benefice, that in ſuch caſe the General averment ſhall not be taken without ſhewing ſpecially how the ſame was his <hi>Lay Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall:</hi>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:54824:4"/>that is to ſay, for him to aver and maintain, that the Tithes he laid claim to, did belong unto him by Parochial right and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, as Miniſter of the place, was no good and allowable plea in Court, but that he muſt ſhew in ſpecial, and in particular, how the ſaid Tithes he laid claim to, became his <hi>Lay Catall;</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by grant, gift, or otherwiſe: So that here is not only an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of the Pope and Clergy, but an Act of Parliament againſt Parochial right and cuſtome of Tithes. And yet ſhould we grant them a cuſtome for Tithes, which they cannot claim without bluſhing; of what weight, how like a feather would it be, being put in the ſcale with <hi>Magna Charta?</hi> And although it may be objected, that they have now a long time enjoyed them, even time out of mind; yet that will not avail much, ſince it is not a lawfull uſer, but an abuſer, and tortious Act, carryed on with a power contrary to all Law, equity and juſtice.</p>
                  <p>Moreover in cuſtomes, <hi>Non diuturnitas temporis, ſed ſoliditas rationis eſt conſideranda,</hi> Not length of time, but ſoundneſſe of reaſon is to be weighed: Upon which ground at a Parliament at <hi>Kilkenny</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> in the 40th. of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. The Iriſh cuſtomes called the <hi>Brehon</hi> Law, though of long continuance, were null'd by that Parliament, upon this ground or Maxim, that <hi>malus u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus eſt abolendus,</hi> an ill cuſtome (as Tith-taking is) ought to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed. So that the plea of a long continued cuſtome of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Tithes, contrary to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> ans common right, will but little conduce to the juſtification of its authority and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſſe. And if from hence, any ſhall fly to Scriptures refuge, which none but avaritious Scioliſts in ſacred law and language will attempt; we ſhall, if the weakneſſe of their own arguments be not a clear confutation of their errors and injuſtice, return a modeſt and ſober anſwer.</p>
                  <p>Secondly and laſtly, as to the other branch of our Petition con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Copy-hold Lands of inheritance, finable and alſo herio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, by the Tyrannicall practiſe of many, at the will of the Lord of the Manor, we humbly conceive, that by the equity of the tenth chapter of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> Let no man be diſtreined to do grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſervice for his free Tenement than he ought, grounded upon the 25. ch. of <hi>Levit.</hi> v. 17. Ye ſhall not oppreſſe one another: all thoſe arbitrary and unreaſonable exactions, of Fines and Heriots, exerciſed of late years by Tyrannical Lords of Manors, have been
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:54824:4"/>illegal, and repugnant to the equity, if not the letter of the ſaid Charter, and have run beſide the chanell of charity, law, and juſtice; But becauſe many of late and former times have laboured much to vilifie and obſcure the credit and eſteem of Copy-holders of inheritance, and their tenure, thereby to make way for their pride, avarice, and Tyranny, we ſhall therefore make a little further inquiry into the diſcovery of them. <hi>Bracton lib.</hi> 4. <hi>ch.</hi> 28. ſaith, that <hi>Villenagiorum, aliud purum, aliuà privilegiatum,</hi> Of Villenages, one kind is pure and perfect Villenage, the other a more free, honourable, and privileged. Where note, that Villenage in its proper and genuine ſignification, is nothing but the ſervice of a Husbandman, which may be either honourable or baſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the quality of the perſon and tenure: and therefore he ſaith, Pure or baſe Villenage is that, whereby either a free man or a bond-man ſo holds of his Lord, as that he is tyed to do what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he ſhall command him, not knowing over night what he muſt do the next morning, and always in all things is held to uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainties; and of this ſort is <hi>Littletons</hi> Tenure of Villenage, whoſe large Tract upon that ſubject might well have been ſpared, ſince there were very ſew, if any, even in his time, who held by that baſe and unworthy I enure.</p>
                  <p>Now the other ſort called by <hi>Bracton, Privilegiatum,</hi> Privile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Villenage, or as he termeth it in his 2d. book, and 8th. and and 35th. Chap. <hi>Villanum Soccagium,</hi> qualified Soccage, which is the ſame with <hi>Littletons</hi> Tenure of Copy-holds, where the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants hold their Land by Copy of Court Roll, as <hi>Cook</hi> in his Commentaries upon <hi>Littleton</hi> 1. <hi>p. Inſt. fo.</hi> 58. acknowledgeth. So that <hi>Bractons</hi> qualified or privileged Soccage, and our Copy-holds, are one and the ſame, which is more clearly proved by the ſame manner of conveyance in alienations: for ſaith he in <hi>li.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>Si Villanus Sockmanus Villanum Soccagium;</hi> if a qualified Sockman or Copy-holder, will convey his qualified Soccage to another, let him ſurrender the ſame unto the hands of the Lord, or his Steward, and let the other receive it from them; which is the form we now uſe. And in his 1. Book and 2d. Ch. they are called <hi>Gleba aſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tii,</hi> Inrolled Tenants of the Glebe or Manor, and who did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy ſuch privileges, as that they could not be put out, ſo long as that they paid their certain and yearly penſions, whoſoever was Lord; neither might they be compelled to keep their Tenement.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54824:5"/>but might alien when they pleaſed, and they them, as we now, did hold their Tenements, <hi>ad voluntatem Domini, ſecundum conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem Manerii,</hi> at the will of the Lord, according to the cuſtome of the Manor: Yet was not that ſuch an unbridled will, as many pragmatical Novices in Iuriſprudential Learning now Imagine, not a naturall will, but a legall will, bounded by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Law and cuſtome; So that if the Lord of the Manor did at any time goe about to diſturb, or put them out of their Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, although they might not have an Aſſize, yet they had <hi>Parvum breve de Recto ſecundum conſuetudinem Manerii,</hi> a ſmall writ of right, according to the cuſtome of the Manor, for to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain their Eſtates. <hi>Bracton lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap</hi> 2. <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 2 where the writ is likewiſe expreſſed. And in his 4th. book and 28 Chap. He ſaith, That if the Tenant be ejected by his Lord, he ſhall have a jury impannell'd, to enquire of the Covenant, and conſent of the Lord, in admitting of him to be his Tenant, whom he ejected, and he ſhall be reſtored; becauſe, <hi>Jura non debent juvare dominum, contra voluntatem &amp; conſenſum ſuum, quia ſemel voluit conventio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem,</hi> The Laws ought not to relieve the Lord againſt his own will and conſent, becauſe he hath made a Covenant, that his Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Tenant ſhall enjoy his Tenement, performing his ſervices and cuſtomes, <hi>li.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. and <hi>li.</hi> 4 <hi>cap.</hi> 28. And in the Reign of <hi>E.</hi> 3. and <hi>E.</hi> 4. Sir <hi>Iohn Danby</hi> and <hi>Thomas Brian</hi> Lord chief Juſtices, were of opinion, that Copy-holders ejected by their Lords, might have an action of Treſpaſſe. Neither is <hi>Bracton</hi> ſingle in his good eſteem of privileged Sockmans, or Copy-holders, ſince <hi>Fieta</hi> writ by a great Lawyer about <hi>E.</hi> 2 his time, and <hi>Ockam</hi> in <hi>H.</hi> 2. his Reign, do both of them honour Copy-holders in thoſe elder times, with the name of cuſtomary Tenants: And <hi>Ockam</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpake worthily of them, but of their Original, whoſe works through the envy and Tyranny of the times, have not had the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to appear in publique. And <hi>Lambard</hi> in his book <hi>De Priſcis An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorum legibus,</hi> of the ancient Laws <hi>England,</hi> ſaith, That Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py-holds were long before the Conqueſt, and then call'd by the name of <hi>Book-land:</hi> and ſince the Conqueſt they have been honoured with many worthy appellations, as of Copy-holders, in <hi>H.</hi> 5. of Tenants by the Rod, in <hi>H.</hi> 4. of Tenants by the Roll, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the will of the Lord, in <hi>E.</hi> 3. of Cuſtomary Tenants, in in <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>Cooks</hi> 1. <hi>p. Iuſt. fol.</hi> 58. And becauſe Copy-holders have
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54824:5"/>been much abuſed in the late corrupt times of Monarchy, not only in the diſgracing of their Tenure, but alſo in the altering and multiplying their Cuſtomes and ſervices: great perſons falſly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending, as if poor Copy-holders had <hi>nil de jure,</hi> but all <hi>de gratia,</hi> nothing of right, but all of favour. Therefore for further ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, we will make ſome brief diſcovery therein. <hi>Bracton</hi> in his firſt Book and ſecond Chapter, ſaith, That the works of privile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Sockmans or Copy-holders were, though ſervile, yet certain and nominated. And again in his 4th Book and 28th Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, That qualified Sockmans had their Tenements granted unto them to hold by Covenant, for certain ſervices and cuſtomes na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and expreſſed, although the ſervices and cuſtomes were ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile; that is with Cart, Plough, or the like, at certain ſet times in the year, according to agreement. And again a little after, <hi>Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lani Sockmanii villana faciunt ſervitia,</hi> Qualified Sockmans do ſervile works and ſervices, yet certain and determined. Now <hi>Cook</hi> upon <hi>Magna Charta, ch. fol.</hi> 13. ſaith, That in theſe words, reaſonable cuſtomes, and reaſonable ſervices, all Fines, whether certain or uncertain, and other Cuſtomes and Duties are comprehended: And if ſo, then for certain all Fines of Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds were in <hi>Bractons</hi> time certain, and not as now uncertain and Arbitrary. But yet by the way take notice, that he doth not ſpeak of any Fines to be paid by Qualified Sockmans, upon death or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienation, that word under that notion being unknown to him or any other (as we conceive) of that age. And having in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Book and five and thirtieth Chapter, treated at large, who ought to do Homage, and who Fealty, and having ſhewed that both free and qualified Soccagers ought to do Fealty to their Lords, comes in the following Chapter to treat of Reliefs: and in the eighth branch of the Argument of that Chapter, makes this Quaerie, <hi>Si de Soccagiis dari debet relevium?</hi> If of Soccages (ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king plurally) a relief ought to be given, which muſt be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood both of free and qualified Soccage; and towards the latter end of the Chapter, ſaith, <hi>Et nunc videndum, ſi de Soccagio dari debet relevium?</hi> And now next comes to be conſidered, whether a Relief ought to be given of Soccage? which being ſpoken inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely, and in generall, without adding any Epithet, either of free or qualified, muſt in all conſtruction, if you conſult the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Chapter, be underſtood both of free and qualified
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54824:6"/>Soccage. So that that duty or performance, which upon the death of the Anceſtor, was given in <hi>recognitionem Dominii,</hi> by way of acknowledgement of his Dominion and Lordſhip; and as he ſaith, <hi>ad relevandam haereditatem,</hi> to relieve and raiſe the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate and Inheritance into the hands of the Heir, was <hi>Praestatio quaedam loco relevii,</hi> a certain preſtation or performance, inſtead of a Relief, (for he will allow it properly to be a Relief, which the Soccager either free or qualified paid) due onely upon death, but never upon alienation, and was ever certain, namely a double Quitrent, that is to ſay, one years Rent due to the Lord, beſides the yearly Quitrent. And this is that Duty as we clearly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, which ſince they have new named and called a Fine, and exacted not onely upon deaths of Copy-holders, but Alienati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons alſo; and not onely according to two years Quitrent, as by Law they ought, but according to their unreaſonable luſts and deſires, forcing from their Tenants not onely two years, but even three years Fine and more, according to the yearly value and Rent of the Land: So that the Copy-holder, who was wont according to the antient Law and Cuſtome, to pay for a Fine upon Death onely, but two years value according to the Quitrent, is now driven to pay two and three years value accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to a full and rackt Rent; and that upon alienations too, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contrary to the ſaid antient Law and Cuſtom, and all good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. Neither is <hi>Bracton</hi> alone in aſcertaining the ſervices and cuſtomes of Copy-holders, but others have ſaid the ſame, and namely <hi>Britton</hi> a Biſhop, in <hi>E.</hi> 1. and very learned in the Laws; and who at the Kings Command compoſed them into a compleat Volum: where treating of Copy-holders of Inheritance, ſetteth it down for poſitive Law, that ſuch were their privileges, that their Lords might neither increaſe their ſervices (under which as before is ſhewed, are comprehended Fines) nor change them, to make their Tenants doe other ſervices or more. <hi>Brit. fo.</hi> 165. And accordingly was the judgement of a whole Parliament in the ſame Kings Reign, though ill, (if not of purpoſe) and vitiouſly tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated; which yet for further ſatisfaction we will here ſet down, as we have received it pointed, and comma'd by <hi>Cook</hi> in his 4th book of Reports, in <hi>Browns</hi> Caſe, in theſe words, <hi>Inquirendum eſt etiam de cuſtumariis,</hi> viz. <hi>quot ſunt cuſtumarii. &amp; quamtum terrae quilibet cuſtumarius teneat, qua opera, quas conſuetudines faciat, &amp; quantum
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54824:6"/>opera &amp; cenſuetudines cujuſlibet cuſtumarii valeant per annum, &amp;. quantum redditur de reddit. Aſſiſae per annum, praeter opera &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudines qua poſſunt talliari, &amp; quae non ad voluntatem Domini,</hi> which in Engliſh according to a true and Grammatical tranſlation, is as followeth.</p>
                  <p>Inquity is to be made alſo of cuſtomary Tenants, that is to ſay, How many cuſtomary Tenants there are, and how much Land every cuſtomary Tenant holdeth, what works, what cuſtomes he doth, and how much the works and cuſtoms of every Cuſtomary Tenant are worth by the year; and how much is paid (meaning by every one) of the Rent of Aſſize by the year, beſides their works and cuſtomes which may be rated and valued; (as two or three dayes work in a year with Plough and Cart) and which are not at the will of the Lord: Whereby it appears, that a whole Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament eſteemed of them as cuſtomary Tenants, that their Rent was accounted then parcell of the Rent of Aſſize; and that all their works and cuſtomes were certain, according to the opinion of thoſe two great Lawyers before-quoted, who lived in or near the ſaid times, one whereof was Lord Chief Juſtice of <hi>England,</hi> and the other a great and learned Biſhop. And for as much as Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders have been as much oppreſſed in Heriots, as in any other duty or ſervice, we will therefore in brief ſpeak a word or two concerning the antient Law in that point. <hi>Fleta lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 50. and <hi>Brit. fo.</hi> 178. both ſay, that the Copy-hold Tenant, making his Teſtament upon his Death-bed, ought to make an acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of his Lord, by giving of him one Heriot. And <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cton lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 26. ſaith, that the Soccager, whether qualified or free, ought at his death to reſpect his Lord with one Heriot, <hi>Quae tamen praeſtatio eſt magis de gratia quam de jure,</hi> which preſtation or performance, ſaith he, is rather of favour than of right, and doth not at all touch the inheritance. And if we look a little higher, <hi>Glanvill</hi> Lord Chief Juſtice of <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>H.</hi> 2. <hi>lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. <hi>De legibus &amp; cenſuetudinibus Angliae,</hi> of the Laws and Cuſtoms of <hi>England,</hi> ſaith in theſe words, <hi>Poteſt quilibet liber homo majoribus debitis non involutus, &amp;c.</hi> Every Freeman not greatly indebted, may in his ſickneſſe make a reaſonable deviſe of his goods under this form, according to the cuſtom of the Country, that he do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his Lord with the beſt and principalleſt he hath; next the Church, and afterwards other perſons, as he pleaſeth: but
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54824:7"/>ſaith he, whatſoever the cuſtomes of diverſe Countries and places are in this point, according to the Lawes of the Kingdom, no man is bound, in his Teſtament to leave any thing to any perſon, but at his free will and pleaſure. For every mans will, ſaith he, is free, as well in reference to Teſtamentarie Laws, as to other Laws. So that here you may plainly perceive, that by the Law of the Land, according to the opinion of this great Iudge, no Heriot was due; and if there were any due by any particular cuſtome, it was but one, and that upon death only, and muſt be given by the Teſtator by Will too, and not be much in debt neither, whereby it appeareth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the opinion of thoſe great Lawyers, <hi>Fleta, Britt. Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cton,</hi> and <hi>Glanvill,</hi> all thoſe Heriots which have been exacted of late in ſuch multiplied numbers, have been illegal &amp; unjuſt, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the good Laws and Cuſtoms of this Nation in former times.</p>
                  <p>Now by what hath been briefly ſaid, it may eaſily appear to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny indifferent man, who hath incroached moſt upon each others Liberties; Whether the great and potent wealthy Lord of the Manor, carrying all things before him by the virtue and charm of his unrighteous Mammon, or the poor deſpiſed trampled-under-foot-Copy-holder, who hath been forc'd to loſe his Liberties, to preſerve his lively-hood. Whereas according to thoſe great au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities of <hi>Bracton, Britton,</hi> and others above quoted, all Fines, Cuſtomes, and other ſervices of Copy-holders, ought neither to be changed nor increaſed; and that according to others, who have ſtrained the Law beyond its due bounds, in favour to Lords of Manors, all unreaſonable Fines and Services are forbidden; and if all unreaſonable, then certainly all Arbitrary, ſince it is abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly made known by long experience to the People of this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that all Arbitrary power, (as is the power of Lords of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, to ſet what Fines they pleaſe upon their Tenants, at Death or Alienation) is oppreſſive, Tyrannical, and contrary to the peace and freedom of this Common wealth, as fully manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in a Declaration of this Parliament, ſet forth in <hi>March</hi> 1648. In theſe words, The Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> elected by the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whom they repreſent, have long contended againſt Tyranny, and endeavoured to remove oppreſſion, Arbitrary power, or pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of will, and all oppoſition to the peace and freedom of the Nation. And again in another Declaration of the 7th. of <hi>April,</hi> 1646. in this manner. And as both Houſes have already for the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54824:7"/>eaſe and benefit of the people, taken away the Court of Wards and Liveries, with all Tenures in Capite and Knight ſervices: So we ſhall take ſpecial care, that as ſpeedy and as great eaſe, may be had otherwiſe in other grievances, as the preſſing occaſions of the Commonwealth will admit. Wherefore (theſe arguments premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, being ſeriouſly conſidered) we humbly crave of your Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, that you would be pleaſed to intercede with our Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative, for the removall of that unjuſt and ſlaviſh bondage and yoke, which neither we nor our fore-fathers have been able to bear, that ſo we may not only in ſpirituals, but alſo in temporals, enjoy that freedom and liberty, which not only by Law, but by right of Conqueſt is due to the wel-affected people of this Commonwealth. It is the Law of Nature; yea and the Law of Chriſt too, <hi>Fac alteri, quod tibi vis fieri,</hi> do to others, as you would be done to. If ſo; How can freedom &amp; liberty be denyed to thoſe who with the hazard and loſſe of their lives, goods, and all, have purchaſed freedome and liberty, not only to their Repreſentatives, and well-affected Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates, but alſo to thoſe who have been enemies to this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth? whereby they, who under the Monarchical yoke were in bondage, not only in reſpect of their eſtates, but of their perſons alſo, are now reſtored to a noble and glorious liberty, whilſt their fellow brethren, who ought to be ſharers in this free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, lye under the burthen of Tithes, and bondage of Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds; many whereof do at this day retain the diſhonourable names of baſe Tenure and Villanage in the worſt ſenſe, as if we were rather returning back to <hi>Egypt,</hi> than in our progreſſe to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan.</hi> Ah moſt religious Sir! did we not <hi>Demas</hi> like mind our own preſent power and profit, more than our truſt and promiſes in times of danger, theſe things could not be: but what ſhall we ſay, <hi>Deus dabit his qui<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> finem,</hi> God will in his due time put a period to theſe things. Now to conclude, we once more humbly deſire your Excellencies favour and aſſiſtance, in gaining freedom to thoſe, who have been greatly inſtrumental in the work of the Lord, and for whoſe ſake paradventure God hath been gracious to this our Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Commonwealth; and we ſhall not only pray for the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall happineſſe of your Excellency, but alſo take the boldneſſe to ſubſcribe, as in all duty and gratitude we are bound,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Excellencies moſt humble Servants in the Lord Christ.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="petition">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:54824:8"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Petition of the Inhabitants of the County of</hi> Middleſex, <hi>concerning Tithes, and Copy-holds of Inheritance, preſented to the Supreme Authority the Parliament of</hi> England.</head>
                  <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                  <p>THat as your Petitioners are really ſenſible of the unwearied la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours this honourable Parliament hath undergone, in the Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of the Rights and Liberties of the free-born people of this Nation, from the incroaching Tyranny of Kingly and Lordly pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, for which they return a gratefull acknowledgement: So they deſire to mind you, that the wel-affected of this Nation, have, in this common cauſe of publique freedom and preſervation, faithfully ſerved you in their ſeverall places, willingly undergoing all bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, either of Tax or Free-quarter; beſides the voluntary loans of very many, even beyond their abilities, upon the Propoſitions. And ſince it is the undoubted right of the free-born people of this Nation, from whom all juſt power is derived, to preſent to their Parliament, or Repreſentative, all their grievances, that ſo Adae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate remedies may be duely applyed; Therefore we offer to your more ſerious conſiderations, theſe enſuing particulars to be ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly redreſſed.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Foraſmuch as all Tithes, reliques of the late deſtroyed Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy, are declared in the 2d. Book of <hi>Cooks</hi> Reports, in the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Wincheſters</hi> Caſe, to be things meerly ſpiritual, and due by divine right; and for which there is no remedy at the Common Law: and alſo in his 2d. Book of <hi>Inſtit.</hi> and Chap. of Tithes, that by the Common Laws and cuſtomes of this Nation, Lands are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decimable:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54824:8"/>which is fully evidenced <hi>by a Canon of the Council of</hi> Lateran, <hi>under</hi> Greg. 10th. 1274. <hi>in this manner; Let no man give his Tithes where he pleaſeth, as before, but let them be paid to Mother Church. And</hi> Britton, <hi>though a Biſhop, treating of Eccleſiaſtical power, and of what things the Church had counſance, doth wholly omit Tithes, knowing very well that thoſe Popiſh Canons and constitutions, which not long before had been made for the taking away the Tenths of mens Estates, were totally void, being Diametrically repugnant to</hi> Magna Charta. <hi>Which likewiſe is further atteſted,</hi> by a decretal Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſent from <hi>Innocent</hi> the 3d. Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> to the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> about the year 1215. wherein it is clearly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, That the free-born people of this Nation, did by the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and till then obſerved cuſtom of this Land diſpoſe of the Tithes or Tenths of their eſtates, according to their own free will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. So that it is very clear, Tithes have been formerly by the Popiſh Clergy ſubtilly perſwaded, or rather extorted from our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, under the notion and conſideration onely of a Divine right, and chiefly by virtue of the ſaid Decretal, which ſo awed our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, that it frighted them into a ſervile and unwilling obedience. Wherefore we humbly deſire that all Tithes and Tenths (under the notion whereof we pay a fifth) may be ſpeedily removed, as a great Oppreſſion and Uſurpation, that ſo Husbandry and Tillage may thereby receive the greater encouragement; and that all Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priators may thereby receive ſuch reaſonable ſatisfaction (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding much may be ſaid to the contrary) as you in your wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms ſhall think fit. And that likewiſe a comfortable mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance may ſome other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd peaceable way according to the Word of God, be provided for the Miniſtry, that ſo the glorious Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt may no longer be impeded, by that ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual and earthly <hi>Remora</hi> of <hi>litigious</hi> Tything, but that Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Meſſengers may with the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> by the ſweetneſſe of their lives and converſation, convince gain-ſayers, that they come not to ſeek ours, but us.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, That all Copy-hold Lands of inheritance, may be made free from all Fines, Heriots, and other ſlaviſh ſervices brought in by, and after the <hi>Norman</hi> Tyranny, as may appear by <hi>Bracton</hi> a great Lawyer in <hi>H.</hi> 3. his time, in his firſt Book and 7th. Chap. of the Cuſtoms of <hi>England,</hi> where he ſaith, That, in the Conqueſt, men held their lands freely, by free ſervices or cuſtomes, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54824:9"/>untill being thrown out by uſurping <hi>Normans,</hi> and their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents, they were enforced to retake them again, to hold by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt and unequal terms and ſervices, yet ſtill certain and nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which through the avarice, cruelty, and oppreſſion of ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Lords of Manors, have been increaſed illegally, to a ſtrange multiplication of Heriots, and Arbitrary raiſing of Fines, from two years value, according to the Quitrent, to two and three years value according to the ſull Rent, a thing altogether unreaſonable, and unconſcionable, as hath been clearly adjudged. And although your Petitioners humbly conceive, that Copy-holders of inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, ought by their Tenures to have been protected by their Lords, and to have been freed in this time of War, from all pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick burthens, and taxes; yet ſo far have they been from affording the ſame unto them, that they have for the moſt part, forſaken and denyed them protection, whereby their Copy-hold Tenants by them deſerted, have for a great part moſt willingly adhered to the Commonwealth, and have laid out themſelves to the utmoſt, in bearing an equall ſhare in all publick hurthens with the Free-hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, to the impoveriſhing of themſelves, their Wives, and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. And Moreover ſince, as we are informed, much of the Lands ſetled upon Souldiery for their Arrears, are freed from all Tithes, Fines, and other ſlaviſh ſervices, which we envy not, but exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly congratulate; nay ſince all Lands held in Capi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e and Knights ſervice, are by an Act of this preſent Parliament freed from all ward-ſhips, and other ſlaviſh imcumbrances, notwithſtanding the greateſt benefit thereof doth redound to the advantage and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molument of thoſe who have bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ctual Armes againſt the State, or who at leaſt in their declared affections have been ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter enemies thereof: Seeing we ſay, that not only the Army, but your enemies have taſted ſo deeply of your grace and favour, Let it not be ſaid in <hi>Gath,</hi> nor publiſhed in the ſtreets of <hi>Aſcalon,</hi> that your deareſt Friends, thoſe out of whom your Armies have been raiſed, formed, and ſupplied with men and money all along; thoſe by whom you have in the greateſt danger, and times of exigency, been moſt readily and willingly aſſiſted, even to the hazard and loſſe of their lives: Let it not be ſaid, we humbly reiterate, that thoſe who have been your friends, Gods friends, and their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries friends, ſhould now at length be left to remain in bondage, and <hi>Gibeonitiſh</hi> ſlavery, whilſt their enemies riot and abound in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54824:9"/>and freedom. Wherefore we humbly deſire, that all Copy-holders of Inheritance, may according to your ſeverall Declarations of the 7th. of <hi>April,</hi> 1646. and of <hi>March,</hi> 1648. be reſtored to chriſtian freedom and liberty, the fruits of Conqueſt, and the juſt reward of their expence and haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, that ſo of victors they may not become ſlaves and vaſſals in their eſtates, to their conquered Lords, whom they begin already to feel, and are dayly like to find more cruell and unreaſonable, than ever, if they ſhall return again to reign over them, with the full ſayl of uſurped power.</p>
                  <p>Thus hoping that the ſame God, who hath even mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly given you Victory over your enemies, reſt from warres, peace in your Habitations, and put a power into your hands to do righteous things for the good of this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, will alſo put into your hearts and minds, to do theſe things repreſented unto you; and what elſe, you in your wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms ſhall know to be for the good and welfare of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And we ſhall ever pray, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="text">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Caſe of Copy-holders ſtated, according to the</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Quando lex accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datur ad cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam &amp; perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam, &amp; non è contra. <hi>When the Law is applyed to the cauſe and perſon, not they to it.</hi>
                     </note> Lesbian <hi>Rule of the Law, in the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt times of Monarchy; wherein is clearly proved, that no Lord of a Manor of Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds of Inheritance, can take for a Fine where (as they ſay) uncertain, of his Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Tenant two years clear yearly value of the Land.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FIrſt, Becauſe it is reſolved by <hi>Popham</hi> Chief Juſtice, <hi>Clench, Gaudy,</hi> and <hi>Fenner,</hi> Juſtices of the upper Bench in the 42. and 43 <hi>Eliz.</hi> between <hi>Hubbard</hi> and <hi>Hammon;</hi> that if the Fines of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54824:10"/>Copy-holders of a Manor are incertaine upon admittan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, yet the Lord may not demand or exact an exceſſive or unreaſonable Fine; and if he doth, the Copy-holder may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to pay it without forfeiture; and according to this reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it was then ſaid, that it had been formerly adjudged in the ſame Court, in one <hi>Hoddeſdons</hi> Caſe. <hi>Cookes</hi> Reports, <hi>lib.</hi> 4to.</p>
                  <p>Now it is a Rule and Maxim, that all exceſſiveneſſe is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred in Law; and that all things ought to be interpreted with equity and moderation. As put caſe, the Lord of a Manor, where Fines, through his Tyranny are incertain, hath taken time out of mind, about a years value, not much under nor over: If there one of his Copy-hold Tenants ſhall improve his Land by great charge and induſtry, from 5 l. <hi>per annum,</hi> to be worth 20 l. <hi>per annum,</hi> and then dye, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Lord ſhall ſet two years Fine, <hi>viz.</hi> 40 l. upon his Heir, this will be an exceſſive and moſt unreaſonable Fine. Firſt, Becauſe where a Lord hath uſually taken about a year, though a little under or over, there to take a year and half, (though according to the value before improvement) is exceſſive, and ſo illegall; if the Rules of right reaſon, moderation and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, were cloſely held to and kept. Next, it is altogether unreaſonable, becauſe, through this improvement of the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, with a vaſt expence and charge, perhaps treble to the Land, the Lord now comes to take in a little compaſſe of time, at a year and halfs Fine, ſix years years value, at two years Fine, eight years value according to the yearly Rent and worth of the Land before improvement: So that now a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous and unconſcionable Lord, (as too many there are) will take advantage to enrich himſelf out of the Tenants vaſt expence and induſtry, contrary to the Rules of Iuſtice, equity and honeſty.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, and laſtly, no Lord of a Manor can by the preſent Law, take two years clear yearly value for a Fine, where (as Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers ſay) they are uncertain, (though repugnant to thoſe great Authorities in the Letter before recited, and contrary to their own Maxims, and abundantly ſavouring of tyranny) upon the admittance of a Copy-hold Tenant, as is clearly reſolved in an action of Treſpaſſe between <hi>Stallon</hi> and <hi>Brady,</hi> commenc'd
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54824:10"/>in the firſt year of King <hi>Iames,</hi> in the Court of Common Pleas; where the Lord of the Manor did ſet a Fine at two years clear yearly value, which the Tenant denying to pay, being unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, the Lord enters, and thereupon the Tenant brings an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Treſpaſſe, and after five years demurre, conſultation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing had with all the ludges and great Lawyers of <hi>England,</hi> it was at length <hi>(viz.)</hi> in the ſixth year of King <hi>Iames,</hi> by the Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the ſaid Court of Common Pleas, fully and unanimouſly reſolved, that the ſaid Fine of two years was unreaſonable, and ſo no forfeiture by the Tenants denial.</p>
                  <p>Now from hence it muſt be concluded that for any Lord of a Manor to demand a year and a halfs Fine, is the very utmoſt rigour and extremity of the Law, as it hath flowed to us out of the impure fountain of Monarchy, and all thoſe who have exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted more, have done illegal, and unwarrantable Acts, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that <hi>Lesbian</hi> Rule.</p>
                  <p>But where Tenants have at their great charge, made im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements as is above declared, there for the Lord to take a year, much more a year and half, is altogether unconſcionable, and againſt the Rules of equity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:54824:11"/>
                  <head>The Caſe of intolerable Oppreſsion in point of Heriots.</head>
                  <p>A Copy-hold Tenant holds a 100. Acres of Land, worth <hi>per annum</hi> 5 s. per Acre, and 20 s. Rent yearly, and for which, the Lord claims a Heriot upon Death. The Tenant aliens his Land to a hundred men; now by our Book-Law, made in corrupt times meerly in favour of Lords, and to oppreſſe poor people, the Lord of the Manor ſhall have his 20 s. Rent, and beſides, a Heriot for every Acre upon the death of every particular Tenant; for this reaſon, which is no reaſon, becauſe a Heriot is an indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible ſervice: ſo that it may ſo fall out, that the Lord ſhall have Heriots in a ſhort time, to the value of one thouſand pounds, whereas the whole is not worth five hundred pounds; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, a poor man having an Acre of his Land not worth five pound, and dying ſeiſed, the Lord ſhall enter upon his Goods, and take away for a Heriot, a Cow or Horſe worth ſix or eight pound, to the utter ruine of his Wife and Children.</p>
                  <p>Now from a diviſion of Land to urge a multiplication of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots, hath neither antient Law, reaſon nor honeſty in it, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding thoſe ſlight Arguments, and fond diſtinctions of Heriot Service, and Heriot Cuſtome, which are uſed to the contrary.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="errata">
                  <p>REader theſe names ſhould have been placed at the end of the 13th Page.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Col. <hi>Pride,</hi> 
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Aug. Wingfield,</hi> 
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Robert Cromwell,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Col. <hi>Potter,</hi> 
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Henry Arundell,</hi> 
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Nich: Beale.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:54824:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Vindiciae Medio-Saxonicae,</hi> OR, Tithes totally Routed, BY MAGNA CHARTA IN A Reply to an Anſwer of <hi>Middleſex</hi> Letter and Petition, in the latter end of a Tract, called, <hi>A Treatiſe of Tithes.</hi> WHEREIN The Invalidity of the ſaid Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſers Arguments are fully manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, and the ſaid Letter and Petition clearly vindicated from Error and Miſtake. BY AUG. WINGFIELD, A Member of this preſent PARLIAMENT.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>F.L.</hi> for <hi>William Larnar,</hi> at the <hi>Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more</hi> near <hi>Fleet-Bridge,</hi> 1653.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:54824:12"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54824:12"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Tithes totally routed, by</hi> Magna Charta.</head>
                  <p>HAving peruſed a Treatiſe of Tithes penn'd by way of Anſwer to its Opponents, by one, as it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, of the long Robe; we thought fit to give timely admonition, that though he pretend to be a wel wiſher to Religion and Propriety, yet when he ſpeaketh fair, men believe him not; for there are, it is to be feared, ſeven Abominations in his heart, who though his <hi>Sophiſticated Arguments</hi> be covered with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, yet ſhall his wickedneſſe be ſhewed before the whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation. <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.25, 26.</p>
                  <p>In his Epiſtle to the Reader, he diſcovers both his ſpirit and his pride, cenſuring his Antagoniſts, as clamorous malitious ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norants, though perhaps in the judgement of unbiaſed Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators, more learned, peaceable, and more Evangelically ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited than himſelf. But fearing leſt his great <hi>Diana</hi> Tithes, the Nurſery of contention and ſtrife, ſhould in theſe days of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and reſtauration of publique Freedom and liberty, like <hi>Dagon</hi> before the <hi>Ark,</hi> fall to the ground and come to nought; he hath therefore, out of his worldly wiſdom, judged it very op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune (both in reference to himſelf and alſo to his Clients the Tith-taking Prieſthood and Impropriator) in this extremity of time, to force into his Aid a Catalogue of Acts of Parliament, though to little purpoſe, ſince few of them before the Statutes of <hi>H.</hi> 8. intimate ſo much as a right, much leſſe command the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Parochial Tithes to Prieſts or others, as if this Reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent would make us all beleeve, that <hi>Ubi nomen Decima, ibi ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentum Decimandi,</hi> that whereſoever in any Statute the word
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:54824:13"/>Tith is found, there is an argument for Tithing: though by his leave in ſome of them by him quoted there is not ſo much as the name
<note n="*" place="margin">Mag. Char. c. 1. Marl. c. 5. 25 E. 1. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> E. 1. &amp;c.</note>: But although he and his Tith-taking Brethren have a long time, like <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Dovi,</hi> confederated to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, not only to make us ignorants, but ſtill to keep ſo, by perſwading of us and our fore fathers, That Tithes were firſt due by Divine Law, then by Canon Law, and now by Statute Law; yet are we and the good people of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> reſolved to be no longer deluded by them with their Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſms, and deceitfull reaſonings.</p>
                  <p>And therefore that we may no longer digreſſe by way of preface, we ſhall now come to reply, and to examine thoſe two grand objections, which the Author of the ſaid Treatiſe raiſeth againſt the <hi>Middleſex</hi> Letter and Petition in the Expoſitory o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening of thoſe two Statutes of <hi>Magna Charta. ch.</hi> 29. and 1. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>ch.</hi> 14. where this Reſpondent ſaith <hi>pag.</hi> 13. That for the Penner of the ſaid Letter and Petition to make the People believe, that the payment of Tithes is againſt <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> is ſuch an expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as was never made upon that Statute, and therefore to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie this Errour (as he calls it) he hath laboured, though in vain, to overthrow the ſaid expoſition, and thoſe invincible ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments built upon it, and to ſet up his own contrary interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and falſe affertion, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That Tithes and the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof by the people, were confirmed by <hi>Magna Charta, ch.</hi> 1. under the Notion of Church rights.</p>
                  <p>And firſt for proof thereof he ſaith, <hi>pag.</hi> 14. That by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law of this Land, at the confirmation of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> Eccleſiaſtical perſons had remedy to recover their Tithes in the Spiritual Court, and then concludes, that the Law gives no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy but where there is a right: which aſſertion is very untrue. For <hi>Cook</hi> upon Tithes ſaith, That by the Common Law Lands are undecimable, and if undecimable, then certainly by that Law there can be no Church right to Tithes, neither to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered by virtue thereof in the Spiritual, or Popes Court, Since the people of <hi>England</hi> were not bound in Law by his Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons. Neither is <hi>Cook</hi> ſingle in his opinion, For <hi>Selden fo.</hi> 291 ſaith, That Arbitrary diſpoſition of Tithes uſed by the Laity, as well <hi>de jure,</hi> of right, (as the poſitive Law then received and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:54824:13"/>practiz'd was) as <hi>de facto,</hi> of deed and practiſe, is that which <hi>Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leff</hi> remembred in his Complaint to the King and Parliament un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>R.</hi> 2. The ſubſtance whereof in brief, is, That the proud and pompous Prieſts did conſtrain the poor People of <hi>England</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> by Popiſh Canons) to pay their Tithes unto them, whereas within a few years before, they paid their Tithes and Offrings at their own free will and pleaſure. Which is alſo atteſted by <hi>Lud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi> a Judge of Aſſize in <hi>E.</hi> 3. who ſaith, That in antient time a man might give his Tith to what Church he would; which is true ſayes Judge <hi>Brook</hi> in Abridging the caſe. <hi>Selden fol.</hi> 252.</p>
                  <p>And the ſaid Author further ſaith, <hi>fo.</hi> 290. That under <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> the 3d. it was uſuall in fact for Laymen by the practice of the Law at that time both Common and Canon, to convey the right of their Tithes, as Rent-charges or the like, to what Church or Monaſtery they pleaſed, and ſuch Conveyances were clearly good. And whereas the Author of the ſaid Treatiſe, <hi>p.</hi> 14. quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> for his Authority of Parochial right, he is clearly miſtaken, ſince Mr. <hi>Seldens</hi> judgement in the ſame place immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately following is cleerly to the contrary, and that which is here alleged as the Treatiſers main Argument, is nothing but the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Canoniſts recited by Mr. <hi>Selden,</hi> and by him in the ſame and following pages fully confuted, <hi>pag.</hi> 144, 146.</p>
                  <p>Moreover <hi>Magna Charta</hi> is, by Act of Parliament made in 25 <hi>E.</hi> 1. called, the Confirmation of the Charters, adjuged and declared to be the Common Law of the Land; which if true, as it is moſt true, then Tithes being not ſo much as named, much leſs confirmed by <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> are not due by the Common Law, (as the ſaid Reſpondent weakly ſuppoſeth) and ſo not at all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Eccleſiaſtical cogniſance.</p>
                  <p>But he objecteth and ſaith, That Tithes are contained in theſe words, <hi>The Churches Rights, Mag. Char. cap.</hi> 1. for further ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction whereof, ſee <hi>Cooks</hi> expoſition upon the very ſame words, where he ſaith, that Eccleſiaſtical perſons ſhall enjoy their lawfull juriſdictions, and other their rights (but not one word of Tithes) without diminution, and that no new Rights were given unto them hereby, but ſuch as they had before confirmed: Now if no new Rights were given, then not Tithes, ſince the Author of the ſaid Treatiſe confeſſeth <hi>p.</hi> 14. that the Common Right of Tithes due to the Rector of the Pariſh, is but from the time of K.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54824:14"/>
                     <hi>John,</hi> and then, as M. <hi>Selden</hi> (whom he quoteth) <hi>p.</hi> 146. decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, not ſo much as in opinion eſtabliſhed, whereby it is evident, not onely by <hi>Selden</hi> and his own confeſſion, but alſo in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Gook,</hi> that at the confirmation of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> Tithes were not at all comprehended in the Rights of the Church.</p>
                  <p>Which will yet more fully appear if we conſult Mr. <hi>Seldens</hi> book of Tithes, and the Roll of <hi>Winten.</hi> In the firſt whereof <hi>pag.</hi> 137. It is delivered for a clear truth, that there never was any Canon of any General Council as yet found, that purpoſely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded payment of Tithes, nor any that expreſly ſuppoſed them a duty of Common right, before the Council of <hi>Lateran,</hi> under Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the 3d. 1615: So that at the Council of <hi>Lateran,</hi> which was in the latter end of K. <hi>John,</hi> and but 12 years or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts before the confirmation of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> by <hi>H.</hi> the 3d. Tithes were not due by common right, that is by Common Law, and ſo conſequently no rights of the Church. And if not then due by Common Law, then certainly not at the confirming of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> ſince in the judgment of all, both Canoniſts and Common Lawyers, 12 years is not a competency of time, either for cuſtom, or preſcription, the one allowing 40 years at leaſt, the other time out of mind.</p>
                  <p>And yet to proceed, this Reſpondent doth further acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>p.</hi> 14. that there was no Parochial Right of Tithes till af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Council of <hi>Lateran</hi> aforeſaid, 1615. and that after the Decretal Epiſtle of <hi>Innocent</hi> the 3d ſent to the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> in the year aforeſaid, the right of Tithes was allowed (but you muſt know by whom, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Pope and his Clergy, not the People) and ſo became <hi>Lex Terrae,</hi> a Law of the Land, which are likewiſe the words and judgement of <hi>Cook:</hi> Now of what force and validity, a Right of Tithes, grounded upon a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of the Pope, and diametrically repugnant to <hi>Magna Charta</hi> can be, let all men judge; ſince <hi>Cook</hi> their Oracle hath declared in his Chapter of Tithes, that all Canons which are againſt the Common Law, or Cuſtom of the Land, are of no force.</p>
                  <p>Now as to the Roll of <hi>Winton,</hi> called by ſome <hi>Doomſday Book,</hi> which was a ſurvey of all the Lands &amp; Revenues both of Clergy &amp; Laity, exactly taken by Commiſſ. in every County throughout the Nation, and returned into the Exchequer about the latter end of the <hi>Conquerours</hi> Reign, It is there Recorded in particular what
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54824:14"/>the Revenues and dues of every Presbyter and Church were, but yet notwithſtanding very rarely, if at all, are any Tithes found among the Church Revenues. So that bence it is moſt cleer, Firſt, that in <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Conquerrors</hi> time, Tiths were no Revenue nor rights of the Church; nor yet Secondly, in <hi>H.</hi> 2. his time, ſee the Letter and Petition, <hi>p.</hi> 5. And laſtly, by the Authors own confeſſion they became due onely but from the latter end of K. <hi>Johns</hi> Reign, and that grounded meerly upon a Popiſh Canon, contrary to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> which is acknowledged by the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to be the Common Law of <hi>England,</hi> both before and after the Conqueſt.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond and laſt objection which the Author of the ſaid Treatiſe maketh, is upon our expoſition of the Statute of 1 <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. which wee ſhall here make good to be moſt genuine and true, notwithſtanding his falſe calumniation; and that his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti expoſition is moſt abſurd and falſe, and ſuch as had not Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom wrought another Nature in him to ſpeak and write untruly, could never have fell from him. Now the queſtion between us is, whether the <hi>Averment</hi> there ſpoken of be Lay <hi>Averment,</hi> and ſo to be made by the Plaintiff, according to his expoſition, or Church <hi>Averment,</hi> and ſo to be made by the Defendant, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our expoſition: whether of which is moſt true, we ſhall leave to every one to judge, by opening unto you the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>Averment</hi> out of the judgment of the Learned, and by holding forth ſuch reaſons as ſhall in brief be produced.</p>
                  <p>And firſt <hi>Cowells Interpreter</hi> ſaith, That <hi>Averment</hi> ſignifieth (according to the Author of Terms of the Law) an offer of the Defendant to make good or to unſtifie in exteption pleaded in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batement or bar of the Plaintiffs Act. And Sir <hi>Hen. Smith</hi> in his book of Law <hi>fo.</hi> 359 alſo ſaith, That <hi>Averments</hi> muſt be offered to be proved true in Barrs. 1. Anſwers, Replications, Rejoinders, &amp;c. but not in Counts andDeclarations. And of the ſame judgment is Sir <hi>Edw. Cook,</hi> in his firſt part of Inſtitutes <hi>fo,</hi> 362. So that it is evident, <hi>Averments</hi> are properly to be made by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendants in their anſwears, or in after pleadings, and not by Plaintiffs in their Declaration: unleſſe in ſome few particular caſes, of which this is none, as is evident, not only by the Grammatical, and Logical Conſtruction of the ſaid Statute, but
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54824:15"/>even in the judgement of Learned <hi>Raſtal,</hi> a Iuſtice of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-pleas, in Q. <hi>Maries</hi> days; who to put the queſtion out of doubt, hath ſet it down in the margent of his Abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Statutes, to be Church <hi>Averment,</hi> which we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to be a final determination of the queſtion.</p>
                  <p>And as to your Ordinance of <hi>Nov.</hi> 1644. for the payment of Tithes, we clearly conceive it to be the judgement of all the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that it is of no longer validity than during Parliamentary Seſſion, which is now diſſolv'd upon ſure grounds of Piety, Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique freedome, right reaſon, and honeſtie: and that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>without the Generall conſent of the major part, either prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, or ſubſequent, of the Supreme Authority, the People.</p>
                  <p>Now by what hath been ſaid it will eaſily appear who doth moſt abuſe and miſlead the People, and whether expoſition of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> and the other Statute of <hi>R.</hi> 2. is moſt true. That of the Letter and Petition, back'd with right reaſon, and the Authorities of great Lawyers and learned Iudges, or that of the Author of the Treatiſe, being a fancy of his own brain, and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed out of implicite Terms, which he that believs, had need of of a Popiſh and implicite faith.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:54824:15"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
